Guide to the Henry E. Rauch Papers, 1963-1992 UA.29.02.0249
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henry E. Rauch papers
1963-1992
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rauch, Henry E.
UA.29.02.0249
2 Linear Feet
Henry E. Rauch was an accountant, businessman, and executive who served on the Board of Trustees of Duke University. An executive and Chairman of the Board at Burlington Industries, he served on Duke's Board of Trustees from 1964-1974. He largely was responsible for the Trustee response to the Duke Vigil in 1968 and closely involved with the expansion of the Duke Medical Center from 1970-1978. The Henry E. Rauch papers include materials related to Henry Rauch's time as a member of the Duke University Board of Trustees, some autobiographical notes on Henry Rauch's personal and professional life, and excerpts from Board of Trustee meeting minutes related to Henry Rauch. Much of the material related to Rauch's tenure in the Board of Trustees was gathered together as a scrapbook, and includes correspondence, clippings, photographs, reports, and typed notes on his particular role and involvement in events, such as the Duke Vigil and in the development of the Duke Medical Center.
Related Materials
Vice President for Business and Finance Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Board of Trustees Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
William G. Anlyan Papers, Duke University Medical Center Archives.
Duke Vigil Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Labor Unions Reference Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Douglas M. Knight Papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
A. Kenneth Pye, Chancellor, Records and Papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Collection Overview
The Henry E. Rauch papers include materials related to Henry Rauch's time as a member of the Duke University Board of Trustees, as well as some autobiographical notes on Henry Rauch's personal and professional life. Much of the material related to Rauch's tenure in the Board of Trustees was gathered together as a scrapbook, and includes correspondence, clippings, photographs, reports, and typed notes on his particular role and involvement in events, such as the Duke Vigil and in the development of the Duke Medical Center. Also included are excerpts from Board of Trustee meeting minutes relating to Henry Rauch, often including handwritten annotations by him.
The collection is arranged into five series: Autobiographical materials, Duke Scrapbooks, Board of Trustees meeting minutes excerpts, Photographs, and Awards. Autobiographical materials include copies of typed chapters describing Henry Rauch's personal and professional life not including his involvement with Duke University. Duke Scrapbooks include materials which were gathered into scrapbooks by Henry Rauch and were disassembled prior to their transfer to the University Archives; these include materials related to Rauch's involvement in Board of Trustees committees, particularly related to the Medical Center and the Duke Vigil in 1968. Board of Trustees meeting minutes excerpts relate to the actions and contributions of Henry Rauch, and many include his handwritten annotations and explanations. Photographs and Awards both include oversized materials, many of which are mounted on boards and were removed from frames. These relate to Rauch's involvement with the Board of Trustees, the Medical Center Board of Visitors, and outside organizations.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Records of the University’s Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Historical note
Henry E. Rauch was born September 21, 1902, near Boston, Massachusetts. The youngest of five children, he began working odd jobs while still in grammar school. He attended the Boston High School of Commerce, where he could study accounting. In 1918, while still in high school, he began working in the office of the Bentley School of Accounting and Finance, later Bentley College. After graduating high school in 1920, Rauch entered the Bentley Evening Division and graduated in 1924 with a degree in accounting.
Prior to graduating from Bentley, Rauch began working for the Amoskeag Manufacturing Company, a textile company, starting as a bookkeeper in 1922. He was with Amoskeag for 14 years, progressing rapidly in responsibility. In 1928 he began a seven-year stint overseeing the textile mills in Manchester, New Hampshire. During this time, he was involved in negotiations with members of the company labor union, closely involved with salary negotiations, as well as being a witness to a number of strikes, some violent, during the period 1933-1935. In 1936, he assisted with the liquidation of Amoskeag after it declared bankruptcy and was affected by a massive flood.
From 1936-1938, Rauch worked for Peterzell & Gelles, then began working for the American Thread Company in 1938. He stayed with American for eleven years, rising to Executive Vice President, before resigning in 1949. He then became President of Peterzell & Gelles from 1949-1951, before becoming a consultant for Burlington Mills in 1951. He worked in this capacity for a brief time before becoming Corporate Controller of Burlington Mills, which became Burlington Industries in 1955, and moved to Greensboro, NC. He was promoted to Vice President, Executive Vice President, and Director before becoming Chairman of Burlington Industries in 1962. Rauch oversaw significant growth and expansion of the company before retiring as Chairman in 1967, then resigning from all Board positions in 1970.
Henry Rauch became involved with Duke University in the early 1960s. While his son Dudley Rauch was a student at Duke, Henry Rauch became Chairman of the Parents of Students Committee and Chairman of the Parents of Students Loyalty Fund from 1960-1963. In 1964, he was elected to the Board of Trustees and became an extremely active member. In 1965, he was elected to the Executive Committee of the Board, then in 1966 the Business and Finance Committee (of which he became Chairman in 1972). In 1968, he was appointed to the Investment Committee and as Chairman of the Board of Visitors of the Medical Center, as well as helping to create the Trustee-Faculty Liaison Committee. He also served on two ad hoc committees, the committee that developed the Policy on Pickets, Protests, and Demonstrations, which became effective in 1968, and the committee that formalized the operations of the Private Diagnostic Clinic associated with the Medical Center. In addition, he served as a member of the special committee to formulate plans and establish goals related to the Decade of Destiny, a far-reaching fundraising campaign to improve Duke University’s standing as a research university with a large number of building projects including a new Medical Center. Rauch was elected Vice Chairman of the Board of Trustees in 1970.
In 1968, during the Vigil that took place on the campus quad in the aftermath of the assassination of Martin Luther King, Jr., Henry Rauch was appointed the head of the Trustee-Administrative Committee organized to deal with demands of students and participants in the Vigil, related to the wages and working conditions of non-academic employees. In this capacity, he issued the statement of the committee resolving to increase employee wages and was instrumental in the wage schedule calculations and negotiations. The Policy on Pickets, Protests, and Demonstrations, which Rauch was involved with developing, came about as a result of this incident. Also partially in response to the Vigil, Rauch helped organize the creation of the Trustee-Faculty Liaison Committee.
Beginning in 1970, when Rauch became a consultant to the Medical Center for the purpose of developing a new Hospital, he became increasingly interested in and involved with the operations of the Medical Center. He was closely involved with the financial planning and structuring of the new Duke Hospital building, called G-94 during planning and now called Duke North, and worked closely with Dr. William Anlyan, Vice President for Health Affairs at that time. He gave financial gifts to the Rauch Family Cancer Research Fund, and later to the Henry E. Rauch Arthritis Research Fund. He was appointed an honorary member of the Medical Alumni Association in 1971, the second person to receive this honor, and his contributions were also recognized in the dedication of a conference room in Duke North.
In 1972, at the age of 70, Henry Rauch began to withdraw from several of his many Trustee commitments. In disagreement with investment advisors and frustrated at the slowed pace of committee meetings involving students and faculty, he resigned from the Business and Finance Committee in 1972. Concerned with the financial management of the Hospital expansion and planning, in 1974 he resigned from the Investment Committee, then resigned entirely from the Board of Trustees and all committee work shortly thereafter. He continued in an advisory capacity with the Medical Center Committee from 1974-1978 and remained active in the financial planning of the Medical Center.
The Board of Trustees and Duke President Terry Sanford voted to award Rauch an Honorary Doctorate of Laws in 1975, then to reject his resignation as Trustee and elect him a Trustee Emeritus in 1976.
Henry Rauch met Alice Atkins, a secretary for the Boston office of the Amoskeag Company, in 1928, and they married in 1929. The couple lived in Boston until about 1930, when they moved to Manchester, NH. Daughter Elizabeth Rauch was born January 18, 1936, and son Dudley Rauch was born July 21, 1941. Along with his involvement with Duke University, Henry Rauch was also Chairman of the Board of Trustees of Bentley College, in Boston, Mass., his alma mater, from which he also received an honorary doctorate of laws, and was a member of the Board of Visitors of Charles R. Drew Medical School in Los Angeles, CA. Alice Rauch died October 22, 1974, and Henry E. Rauch died January 16, 1994, of a heart attack.
Provenance
The Henry E. Rauch papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in October 2014.
Student movements -- North Carolina; Civil rights demonstrations -- North Carolina -- Durham; Collective bargaining -- College employees -- North Carolina -- Durham; Hospitals -- Administration; Student participation in administration; Duke University. Medical Center -- History; Duke University. Board of Trustees; Amoskeag Manufacturing Company; Blackburn, John O., 1929-; Burlington Industries, Inc.; Huestis, Charles B., 1920-; Duke Endowment; Sanford, Terry; Duke Hospital -- Design and construction -- Planning; Rauch, Henry E.; Anlyan, William G.; Bentley College; Rauch, Henry E.
- Autobiographical materials, 1978, undated
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this series include six typed chapters written by Henry Rauch regarding his life and memories, and were apparently intended for his children, Dudley and Elizabeth (Betsey). These chapters are titled: "My Early Years," "Amoskeag Manufacturing Company 1922-1936," "Supplementary - Amoskeag 1922-1936 - Our Life in Manchester - Stories re F.C. Dumaine," "The Years Between Amoskeag (1936) and B.I. [Burlington Inudstries] (August 1951)," "Commentary - H.E.R. and B.I.," and untitled Bentley College trusteeship and involvement notes.
  These materials detail both professional events and accomplishments, including financial details of business operations and acquisitions at Amoskeag Manufacturing Company and Burlington Industries, as well as personal and family anecdotes.
  - Autobiographical materials, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Duke scrapbooks, 1963-1992
  The materials in this series were removed from scrapbooks put together by Henry Rauch on his tenure as a member of the Board of Trustees of Duke University, and consist of correspondence, clippings, reports, pamphlets, photographs, cards, and typed notes. The materials were largely in chronological order and had apparently been arranged into three scrapbooks or groupings: Duke 1963-1970, Duke 1971-May 360, 1978, and June 1978-1992. Some of these materials were annotated by Henry Rauch by hand or typed (generally dated). Also included are a few materials related to Bentley College.
  Duke 1963-1970 includes materials related to Henry Rauch's election to the Board of Trustees, including correspondence with Duke President Douglas Knight and clippings on new Trustees; materials on the events surrounding the Duke Vigil, including correspondence and clippings; materials related to the development and adoption of the Policy on Pickets, Protests, and Demonstrations; and materials related to an editorial in the Greensboro Daily News regarding Duke's financial status, including clippings, correspondence, and Rauch's notes regarding his response the editorial. Correspondents of note include Douglas Knight, William Van Alstyne, John Blackburn, Terry Sanford, and other Trustees including Nancy Hanks.
  Duke 1971 - May 1978 includes materials related to Henry Rauch's increasing involvement with the Medical Center, including correspondence, financial analyses, reports and clippings; materials related to Rauch's resignation from commitees and from the Board of Trustees, primarily consisting of correspondence; and other materials. Noted correspondents include Dr. William Anlyan, Charles Huestis, Terry Sanford, and other Trustees.
  Duke June 1978 - 1992 includes materials gathered by Rauch in his capacity as advisor on the Medical Center Committee, and primarily consists of financial reports and analyses and correspondence, as well as materials related to financial gifts to the University made by Henry Rauch, including a service award that was converted into the Henry E. Rauch Arthritis Research Fund.
  Access Restrictions
  50 Year Restriction: Records of the University’s Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
  Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
  - Duke Scrapbook (1963-1970), 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Duke Scrapbook (1963-1970), 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Duke Scrapbook (1963-1970): Items Separated, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Duke Scrapbook (1971 - May 30, 1978) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Duke Scrapbook (1971 - May 30, 1978), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Duke Scrapbook (1971 - May 30, 1978), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Duke Scrapbook (1971 - May 30, 1978), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Duke Scrapbook (1971 - May 30, 1978), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Duke Scrapbook (1971 - May 30, 1978), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Duke Scrapbook (1971 - May 30, 1978), 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Duke Scrapbook (June 1978 - 1992), 1978, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Duke Scrapbook (June 1978 - 1992) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Duke Scrapbook (June 1978 - 1992), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Duke Scrapbook (June 1978 - 1992), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Duke Scrapbook (June 1978 - 1992) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Board of Trustees meeting minutes exerpts related to Henry Rauch, 1966-1974
  Materials in this series consist of copies of Board of Trustees minutes excerpts related to Henry E. Rauch and his work with the Board and its committees. Minutes are from both Board of Trustees meetings and Executive Committee meetings. Many of these excerpts were annotated by Henry Rauch by hand, expanding on or explaining the contents of the minutes.
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes related to Henry E. Rauch, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes related to Henry E. Rauch, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes related to Henry E. Rauch, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes related to Henry E. Rauch, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes related to Henry E. Rauch, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes related to Henry E. Rauch, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes related to Henry E. Rauch, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Board of Trustees meeting minutes related to Henry E. Rauch, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Photographs, 1971-1984, undated
  - Duke Hospital Board of Visitors, undated (Box 2)
  - Henry E. Rauch accepting honorary doctorate from President Terry Sanford at commencement, May 11, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Charles R. Drew Postgraduate Medical School Board of Visitors, September 22, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Henry E. Rauch and Dr. William Anlyan after Henry E. Rauch's election as an honorary member of the Medical Alumni Association, November 19, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Dr. William Anlyan and Henry E. Rauch in front of Henry E. Rauch conference room door at Medical Center, 1984 (Box 2)
- Awards, 1971-1980
  - Duke University Medical Awards, 1971, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Charles R. Drew Postgraduate Medical School Certificate of Recognition, 1975 (Box 2)